Guide to the Efrain Gutiérrez Papers, 1966-1998 M1103
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
Efraín Gutiérrez Papers
1966-1998
M1103
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
3.0 Linear feet
Scripts and production notes related to feature films and proposed projects. Miscellaneous correspondence. Production and business documents: scripts, shooting notes, promotion, box office receipts, contracts, and legal correspondence. Original posters for all three feature films. Photographs. Clippings include local and grassroots publications that are difficult to find elsewhere. These provide a rare opportunity to study grassroots feature film production and distribution.
Gutiérrez, Efrain
Scope and Content
Collections contains scripts and production notes related to feature films and proposed projects, miscellaneous correspondence, production and business documents such as scripts, shooting notes promotion, box office receipts, contracts, and legal correspondence. Also contains original posters for all three feature films, photographs, clippings from local and grassroots publications. This collection provides a rare opportunity to study grassroots feature film production and distribution.
Biography
Efrain Gutierrez is a Chicano filmmaker whose film Don't Bury Me Alive! is the first Chicano-produced feature film. It addressed a number of issues relevant to the Chicano civil rights movement. The film broke the Mexican film industry's monopoly on the Spanish-language theater circuit in the United States. Guiterrez later directed and starred in two other feature films: Amor Chicano es Para Siempre, 1977, and Run, Tecato, Run, 1979.
Provenance
Purchased, 1999.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Chicano Arts Theater.; Mexican American art; Mexican American authors; Mexican Americans; Motion pictures; Photoprints.; Screenwriters.
- Mud racing activities. Includes Photos., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Efforts in support of Chiapas Indians, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Cinema Guild catalogue, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Synopsis for lowrider movie. Handwritten, 7 pgs., Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Story set in 1960 and 1920. Handwritten, 6 pgs., Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Script and support material for My Beloved Republica, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Scripts, synopsis and support material for .Republica, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Scene breakdowns for Run Tecato, Run, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Contracts for rental of Please, Don't Bury Me Alive!, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Contracts/loans for Please, Don't Bury Me Alive!, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Newspaper artwork for three feature films, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Travel expenses for trip to California, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Contracts, music rights, post-production invoice, and business correspondence for Run, Tecato, Run, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Skits and correspondence for Chicano Arts Theater, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Misc. scenes and notes for Run, Tecato, Run, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Promotional materials for Please, Don't Bury Me Alive!, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Documentary synopsis, Zapata Texas, late 1970s (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Spanish-language radio spot and contact information for Please, Don't Bury Me Alive!, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Legal documents related to distribution contract for Please, Don't Bury Me Alive! with Azteca Films, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence with Ernie Brasie, lawyer, re: Please, Don't Bury Me Alive!, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence with universities and schools re: Please, Don't Bury Me Alive!, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Theater bookings and some promotional materials for Please, Don't Bury Me Alive!, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Theater bookings for Run, Tecato, Run, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Misc. story notes, early 1980s (Box 2, Folder 10)
- PSI film laboratory lawsuit against Gutierrez, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Bumper sticker for Amor Chicano Es Para Siempre, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence with filmmaker Fred Garcia, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Misc. correspondence and publicity, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Three color photocopies of photographs: Run, Tecato, Run, La Onda Chicana, and group shot with Gutierrez, late 1970s (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Two issues of Candilejas featuring Gutierrez, 1976 & 1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Appearance bond for Gutierrez from S.A., 1978 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Documents related to father's death, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Misc. college documents and records, Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Booklet for 30th high school reunion, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Documents related to placement of films in the UCLA Film and Television Archive, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Actor's photo, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Cash receipts for expenses, 6/1975-2/1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- First play written by Gutierrez, early 1970s (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Puppet show for Chicano Arts Theater, early 1970s (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Play written by Sabino Garza, early 1970s (Box 3, Folder 6)
- C.A.F.E. business cards, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Stills for Run, Tecato, Run, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Chicano Arts Theater, 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Misc. personal photos, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Misc. documents, Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Low Rider - budget and synopsis, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Chon Noriega - correspondence, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Term paper on Islam, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- High school diploma, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- The Way Back, autobiography of Jesse Galvan, Jr., 1992 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Real estate lien note for C.A.F.E., 1997 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- 1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Legal correspondence for Please, Don't Bury Me Alive!, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Box office receipts for Please, Don't Bury Me Alive!, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Exhibition agreements for Run, Tecato, Run, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Dance audio mix notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Dance editing notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Movie posters and newspaper articles (Box 5, Folders 1-6)